Today we'll be talking about imitation
learning. Great. Um, so as a partial
recap from last time, we started talking
about some of the notation that we use
for representing behavior and
formulating problems as a decision-m
problem. He talks about states and
observations where we either have access
to something that can fairly completely
represent the state of the world or um a
more partial representation that we will
refer to as an observation.
Uh we also will be representing actions
or decisions with uh a t uh and then we
can think about uh a trajectory as uh an
example of behavior that we've taken
over time.
Uh we also introduced this notion of a
reward function which is how good is a
given state uh and action. And uh lastly
this kind of notion of a policy which is
either conditioned on the current state
what actions do we want to take or
conditioned on a history of
observations. What actions should we
take and usually this policy is the
behavior that we're trying to learn.
Um, we briefly mentioned how this kind
of policy can rep be represented using a
generative model and we'll actually
touch on that a little bit more today.
Uh, and the last thing that's not on the
slide is that we talked about how the
goal of reinforcement learning problems
is usually to maximize the expected sum
of rewards. And today we'll be talking
about uh one way to do that by trying to
imitate a good policy. And in
particular, the plan today is to go over
some of the basics for imitation
learning. Then we'll talk about learning
expressive policy distributions and why
that's important for imitation learning.
Uh then we'll talk about learning from
online interventions and time
permitting. We'll talk a little bit
about uh how to collect demonstrations
in the first place. Um yeah so some of
the key learning goals this is a little
bit in some ways kind of orthogonal to
the main topic of the class but it's
actually very important to understand in
order to get performant imitation
learning systems. So we'll be talking
about how to represent distributions
using neural networks rather than
deterministic functions. We'll also be
talking about why expressive
distributions matter for imitation
learning and one challenge that can come
up with imitation learning which is
compounding errors and how to address
compounding errors.
Great. So what is the goal of imitation
learning? Uh like the goal of
reinforcement learning, we want to try
to achieve high reward. We want to get a
good policy that can do the task well.
uh and the way that we'll try to do that
is we'll assume that we're given some
trajectories that are collected by an
expert. This is our data and we'll refer
to these trajectories as demonstrations.
So it's kind of like a special kind of
trajectory that is demonstrating how to
perform the task.
Uh and we'll use uh D to denote these
demonstrations. Um like a trajectory,
it'll be a sequence of states and
actions.
And as an example of what this
demonstration data might look like, if
we wanted to learn how to autonomously
drive a car, we could have
demonstrations that are in the form of
people driving cars because people are
pretty good at driving cars most of the
time. Uh, and so we could record the uh
record from the sensors on a car as well
as record uh kind of steering commands,
acceleration, and so forth. and using a
data set of human drivers driving, we
could then try to mimic that in order to
train an autonomous driving agent.
Um, now we don't know uh we don't know
exactly how humans drive. Uh, we don't
know the policy uh that humans are using
in order to drive. Uh, so we can think
about this demonstration data set as
being sampled from some unknown policy
PI expert.
Uh and then the goal is to learn a
policy that performs uh at the level or
similar to the level of the expert
policy by mimicking what's present in
the demonstration data set. Cool. So
this is the problem setup.
Now um let's think about uh kind of
version zero of how we could try to do
this. So
um kind of a very simple way that we
[laughter] could do this is kind of
first we're given our
uh our demonstration data set.
Uh so this is some data set that
contains
uh state action pairs.
Uh we could think of uh yeah these are
each of the state actions in each of the
demonstration trajectories.
And then we could say that we want to
train some policy to mimic the
demonstration.
So we
would be training some policy and in
particular we could think about uh the
actions that this policy is going to
take. So if we were to uh take one of
the states in our demonstrations and run
it through our policy then we would get
some sort of predicted action a hat. Um
so let's say that this is sampled from
pi theta given a state in the
demonstration
and then we could try to basically say
we want this predicted action to be as
close as possible to the action that the
demonstrator took. Uh so we could then
minimize
the
difference between the predicted action
and the action in the data set. And we
could do this minimization
over all of the states and actions in
our demonstration data set. Once you
train a policy such that the predicted
actions are as close as possible to the
actions in your data set, then
you can just deploy your policy. This is
a policy that should be mimicking
uh the actions in your data set. This is
version zero of imitation learning. So
given demonstrations collected by an
expert,
you essentially do supervised regression
to the expert actions. Um if your policy
is a neural network, this means doing a
forward pass on you sample a mini batch
from here. do a forward pass on your
neural network to get the predicted
actions, compute the loss, and then back
propagate the loss into the parameters
of the neural network. And you do that
iteratively with your favorite
optimizer, some form of stoastic
gradient descent in order to optimize
your policy.
So it's essentially a form of supervised
learning.
Um and then from here you can then
deploy your learn policy and it should
be able to mimic the expert and do
something sensible. Yeah. So in this
case um this case we're considering a
deterministic policy. Yeah. And we're
just essentially yeah doing L2
regression. I guess here I wrote it as a
as a stoastic policy. Um but let's yeah
let's correct that and let's have this
be a deterministic policy.
the expert might not be deterministic uh
and that might lead to some issues. Uh
so let's actually talk about that a
little bit. So uh what could go wrong?
Um let's go back to our driving example.
So we have a data set from human drivers
and we recorded the the states or the
observations. We recorded the steering
commands and any other actions that we
might want to use. And let's say that um
for this particular car uh in some cases
that the some human drivers might decide
to go straight uh and other drivers
might decide to merge left uh maybe
because they want to move to a faster
lane. Um so our data set might contain
both examples of going straight in
situations like this and examples of
merging left in situations like that.
Now
a question for you.
Uh if you train a policy with L2
regression uh on a data set that has
these kinds of examples,
what would a policy that was trained
with L2 regression do in a situation
like this? Yeah. So the policy might go
to the middle of the two lane and let
let's see why that is. So we um
in this example uh say we have the
steering command.
Uh and if we thought about the
distribution over actions that are
covered in the data set for drivers that
chose to go straight, their distribution
of actions would look maybe something
like this where this is like zero
steering command. This is like kind of
staying straight.
And
for the drivers that chose to merge
left, their distribution over actions
for the steering command might look
something like this.
So this is the probability over actions.
And then if we think about the
these are kind of the two examples. This
is if if they're deciding to merge left,
they maybe have a steering command of
-2. This is if you stay straight that
might have a steering command of zero.
And then in your data set the kind of
overarching distribution over actions
represented in the data set might look
something like
this where maybe more likely people are
to go straight than to merge left. But
you get this kind of multimodal
distribution that has two peaks, one at
going straight and one at merging left.
And then when you use L2 regression to
try to fit this kind fit this data, what
it's going to do is it's going to
predict the mean. So it's going to
predict the mean action. And in this
case, the mean action would be something
like here. And that would be probably
not very good action to take uh because
that might kind of straddle the uh um
the the lines on the highway. And also
we can see that this action actually has
very low probability under the data
distribution. So it's also kind of
objectively or mathematically a poor
choice um because it had low probability
under what the data was doing. Yeah. So
L2 regression is is um the equation from
the previous slide. So basically
minimizing this squared loss between the
predicted action and the true action.
And then the other question was what is
the difference between the green and the
red here? So essentially what I'm
drawing in the green is this is the
distribution over kind of expert
actions. Maybe I'll use expert to refer
to that conditioned on only the data
that chose to go straight.
Uh the blue is the distribution over
expert actions
if they choose to merge left.
And then the red is the distribution of
actions
represented in the data set uh for a
given state.
Uh so this is uh the red is actually
what your data looks like. Um and this
is I'm just showing this is what the
distribution looks like for kind of one
part of one subset of drivers and the
other subset of drivers. You're asking
can you sample from the data set um and
do what was in the data set? basically.
Yeah. So, the tricky thing with sampling
from the data set and doing what's in
the data set is that um that would look
kind of like a nearest neighbors
approach kind of within the realm of of
machine learning. And it is in some ways
a viable approach to a number of machine
learning problems. But one big challenge
is that ultimately when the car is
driving uh or when you're kind of have
some sort of autonomous driving agent,
it's going to face scenarios that are
different from what's in the data set.
And uh the
when it's in those uh when it's in those
uh different positions uh you won't
necessarily have examples in your data
set that you can just uh pick from.
So you won't necessarily be able to say
like oh I saw what the expert did in
exactly this situation because uh
ultimately you'll be evaluating
scenarios that are different. So what
would you do if the actions are not
numerical? Uh we will also uh in like a
slide or two we'll talk about discrete
actions as well.
So to go over this example on the
slides, uh we could say that the data
for staying straight is in yellow. The
data for merging left is in blue. Uh the
combined data set maybe because more
people decided to stay straight is shown
in black, the black dotted line. And
then if we train um a model to minimize
the L2 error then it will the
deterministic policy will choose to take
an action that's right here which is the
mean of the black distribution which has
low probability under the data.
Um now you might be wondering how often
does this actually happen in practice.
So like this is kind of maybe maybe you
might think that this is kind of a
contrived example where um there is kind
of variability in what people would do.
Um it turns out that this actions
actually happens all the time. Uh people
and demonstrators often do things in
different ways not just in driving and
not just in like key decision states.
And um this happens especially when data
is collected by multiple people. Uh
because people have different
preferences. they have kind of
underlying ways that they like about
doing things and you can't directly
observe all of those preferences and all
the things that might affect their
behavior.
And so as a result uh there are some
scenarios where if you have like one
expert policy uh that's uh that's kind
of always takes a consistent strategy,
it's okay to use a deterministic policy.
Uh but in many other cases, it's
actually very important to make sure
that you account for this kind of
multimodality in the data.
Uh and so the natural question that
arises from here is instead of just
learning the mean, could we actually
represent learn to represent more of the
distribution of the expert data and not
just the mean?
Cool. Um and so this is where kind of
learning distributions with neural
networks comes in. Uh and in particular,
let's see, let's start a new
new whiteboard. So
in the case of the deterministic policy,
we had some neural network.
I will use a box to represent a neural
network. Uh and we just were taking as
input some state and we're outputting
the mean action kind of the mean of a
distribution. And so because it's only
representing the mean, it's hardly a
distribution at all. Uh, and instead
what we'd like to be able to do is have
this neural network actually output the
kind of parameters
of a distribution
over actions.
And if you can represents
then we should be able to capture more
than just the mean.
Cool. So this is often the way that we
try to learn distributions with neural
networks is we actually output the
parameters of those distributions. So
you can think about it as this. You have
a neural network outputs parameters. Um
if it's if the distribution class that
you choose is very expressive then you
should be able to get a expressive
distribution as output.
Now let's think about a couple examples
of what this might look like. So, um, if
your actions are not continuous and if
instead they are discrete actions, so
maybe you're trying to train a policy to
play a video game like Super Mario,
then the actions might be something like
up arrow, down arrow, press A, press B,
right arrow, something like that. And
what you could do is what it the neural
network could output is basically this
categorical distribution over actions
where it's going to in uh in this
discrete case it will output the
probability of the first action the
probability of the second action the
probability of the third action and so
forth.
uh and so you can think of this sort of
as a classification problem
and this distribution is actually
maximally expressive uh and what I mean
by that is that there isn't any
distribution over actions that this
cannot represent uh because it's a
fairly simple kind of categorical uh or
pretty simple set of discrete possible
options. Um so this is actually really
nice. Uh we can get a really expressive
distribution this way. Uh unfortunately
a lot of the world is not just
one-dimensional discrete action choices.
We often have much more complex actions
and that's why we need to think about um
how to model distributions over those
actions.
So if we move towards continuous actions
um like in a driving scenario where you
have steering commands for example um
the most natural thing to use is to the
most natural thing to do is to use a
gausian distribution. We talked about
outputting just the mean of a gausian
distribution which corresponds to
minimizing the squared error. Um but you
can also have the neural network output
the variance. Uh unfortunately, if you
have it output the variance, it's not
going to do anything uh particularly
helpful uh in this example. It'll just
um output a wider variance gausion in
order to try to cover more probability
mass. Um and it's not very expressive.
Uh and so we want to be able to use
distribution classes that are more
expressive so that we can try to um
ultimately get actions that are high
probability.
Yeah. So the question was um if we have
some action distribution that looks like
this for example um would we be happy if
we can perfectly model this um or would
that still lead to issues where you
might have like an indecisive policy
that chooses one mode and then chooses
another mode. The
um the answer here is that if you're if
you have a good state representation
then you should be happy. uh and in
particular uh say you modeled this
perfectly and for example you chose like
this and then you merge left you start
merging left um then if you know that
you've started to merge left and your
velocity is moving left then the data
should continue moving left and so then
at that point the distribution over
actions should look kind of something
more like this uh once you are in that
state at that point
um so if you have a good demonstration
data set and a good state representation
If you perfectly model the
demonstrations, you will get a good
policy out. So the question is, is the
goal is the only goal in imitation
learning to mimic the expert or is there
some assumption that uh the expert was
maximizing some reward? Um generally you
want you kind of assume that what you're
trying to imitate is good. Uh the
um but it doesn't necessarily need to be
the optimal policy. Uh and in many cases
um like many real world practical messy
scenarios getting the optimal policy is
like hopeless in some ways. Um so yeah
generally we assume that you're trying
to mimic something good and really the
focus is on trying to imitate that.
Yeah. So the question is in this case
like are we happy um if we do this
perfectly and are we happy with sampling
a mode that is under represented? uh
there are scenarios where you might want
to try to essentially do better than the
expert and maybe in some cases this mode
is is actually better or maybe in some
cases this mode is is really better. Uh
if you want to outperform the expert
that's more where reinforcement learning
comes in and other tools come in. You
can also try to curate your data set to
try to contain more of the stuff that
that you think is better. um the uh but
yeah with imitation learning uh
generally everything that we'll talk
about in this lecture is trying to meet
expert performance or meet the
demonstrator performance and not exceed
it. Yeah. So the question is should the
parameters of the distribution over
actions be state dependent and yeah
absolutely I've been writing this as as
kind of the parameters of P of A but
everything here is implicitly dependent
on the state because this is the output
of a neural network um that was
conditioned on the state and so in some
states it might choose to output a
distribution that's really multimodal in
other cases it might choose to output a
distribution that is much more unimodal.
Cool. So let's talk about some more
interesting expressive distributions
with neural networks. Um and some of
these will build upon tools in
generative modeling and in particular if
we think about uh some examples of
generative models. Uh we won't go into
all the details of these uh but one
example of a generative model that you
might have seen before is called a
diffusion model. Uh and this is a model
that can output and and generate images
of different people. It can be used to
generate videos and so forth. is very
popular for generative models over
visual data. And the thing that's really
cool about um these kinds of image
diffusion models is that they are able
to represent a very diverse distribution
over images including images that are
completely different from um from one
another.
Another example of a generative model is
an auto reggressive model. Uh you can
think about this as essentially like uh
what happens with language modeling
where you're predicting one kind of
token or one word at a time.
And this is also a really powerful model
and it's much uh yeah much more powerful
than just outputting the distribution um
the distribution like at the mean and
variance of a gausian and much more
powerful than outputting for example the
categorical distribution over one
dimension.
So you can think about these two as um
most typically used to represent either
the probability of an image given a text
description or the probability of the
next word given the word so far.
And the reason why they're often used in
these contexts is because uh they're
people these are very common problems
that people work on a lot and also
because they're very well suited for
addressing these kinds of problems. But
you don't like the underlying technique
behind image diffusion models and auto
reggressive models is extremely general
and you can use the same idea to learn a
distribution over actions given
observations or given state.
So let's talk a little bit about how we
might uh use some of these tools to
learn that distribution.
So our goal is to approximate p of a
given s. Um one example uh one kind of
maybe form of generative model uh that's
simpler than those two that we'll start
with is a mixture of gausian. Um and a
mixture of gausian is already a lot more
expressive than just a single gausian.
Uh and so it's a case where we're trying
to model a distribution as a combination
of gausian.
And so in this case, instead of just
having the neural output the neural
network output mu, we'll have it output
um the parameters of a gausian mixture
model distribution. And so in the case
of a DMM,
it will output
uh the mean,
standard deviation and weight associated
with one gausian.
Also the mean, standard deviation and
weight of a second gausian and so on. uh
and you might if you have n different
components it will output n different uh
parameters for different gausian.
Yeah. So the question is um can we
elaborate more on uh like what does it
mean for uh these distributions to be
more or less expressive? Yeah. So um
essentially it is referring to um if you
have some underlying distribution. It's
like how um
maybe I'll actually rephrase it slightly
differently. So um one way to think
about it is it's essentially the number
of different distributions you can
capture like perfectly with um with that
chosen representation. And so if you
only use a gausian there then you can
only perfectly model gausian
distributions. Um whereas if you use a a
gausian mixture model you can represent
any individual gausian but you can also
represent um any other dist any
distribution that is can be represented
perfectly as a combination of gausian
and so it's strictly more expressive
than using a single gausian. Now in some
cases it can be difficult to like
compare two different distribution
classes because in some ways some might
be more expressive or less expressive
but in the case of gausian mixture
models it's like strictly more
expressive than a gausian.
Yeah, the question is do you need to
pick the number of gausians ahead of
time? Uh yes, you do. You can think
about it as a hyperparameter and you
could experiment and look at how well
are you fitting the data um with
different numbers of mixture components.
Okay. Um and then there's two other
examples of generative models that we
could use. Um the second one is auto
reggressive discretized and auto
reggressive uh which is just like
language models. And the third would be
to use something like diffusion but
diffusion over actions instead of
diffusion over images.
And so we talked a little bit just now
about mixtures of gausian where we'll be
outputting basically the parameters of a
gausian mixture model.
Um now let's talk a little bit about
uh kind of the a scenario where we could
try to use an auto reggressive model
like a language model in order to
generate action.
So uh in this case
there's a couple scenarios where you
might want to use this. So you might
have you might be in a scenario where
your actions are already discrete
and you actually don't need to
discretize in that case. Um or you might
be in a scenario but but where it's uh
multi-dimensional or you might be in a
scenario where they are actually
continuous and multi-dimensional and
then you need to discretize or tokenize
first and then use an auto reggressive
model. And so if we think about this
back in the driving example so this will
be
uh if we use discretize plus
um auto reggressive
In this case, let's say that we're in
the driving case and
we'll just consider a simplified driving
case where the first action is the
steering angle
and the second action is the
acceleration.
So if we wanted to represent a
distribution over these actions using an
auto reggressive model, there's two
things that we would want to do. Um the
first would be to discretize and the
second then would be to formulate the
auto reggressive model. And in
particular when we use auto reggressive
models, it means that we're going to be
essentially predicting one dimension at
a time. So if we first want to model a
distribution over the first dimension of
the action, what we would do is um in
the case of steering. So we have um
p steering
say that the um we wanted our prediction
to look something like this.
Uh now a gausian can't represent this
and so we would choose to discretize it
and represent a discretized distribution
and what that would look like is
essentially kind of creating bins for
the different steering angles
and you would then output a probability
for
each bin. [clears throat]
And then
this kind of something that looks a
little bit closer to like a staircase.
um these bars would be the distribution
that you're actually using to
approximate the original distribution.
And so you could then in this case uh
output so for the first dimension you
would be outputting each of the
probability values for each of these
bars like the height of each of these
bars.
So this gives you a fairly expressive
distribution over angle. And then you
could choose to have a more fine
discretization or a more coarse
discretization. And if it's more fine,
you get more expressivity in terms of
what you can represent. But you also
have to output more numbers. So there's
a trade-off there. And then once you
output a distribution over the angle,
then you would want to output a
distribution over acceleration.
uh and in particular uh in the case of
merging left versus going straight, if
you're merging left, probably you would
be accelerating more because there was a
car kind of back into the left. Whereas
if you're going straight, you're
probably more likely to be um more
likely to be kind of keeping your
current speed. And so there's
essentially kind of um we want our pro
our distribution over acceleration to be
conditioned on which angle which
steering angle we chose.
So um what we will do is we'll predict
kind of P angle and then we will sample
a a steering angle from this. We'll
refer to this for now as a T1 because
it's the first dimension of the action.
We'll sample it from this distribution
here.
And then we want to get a distribution
over the second dimension
conditioned on the first dimension.
And to do this, we'll then pass our
predicted action or the sampled action
back into our model and then have our
model output another distribution. Um
and in this case if you um if you are
conditioning on
a t1
equals uh maybe an angle that's like -2
so something more left then you might
output a distribution over acceleration
that is kind of more
uh
has more probability on higher
accelerations versus If you condition on
an ex a steering angle that is something
more like zero, then you might output a
distribution over accelerations
that is
smaller. Yeah. So the question is how do
you build your training data when you
are discretizing like this? So
to do this um
let's see. So um when you build your
training data, you'll have the state
action pairs and you'll be sampling
state action pairs and the
in order to kind of convert it into
something like this. What you'll do is
you'll sample a state action pair and
then you'll bin the action according to
your binning strategy and then you'll
apply a a loss to that um is between the
model's predicted distribution and the
sampled action which would be like one
of these bins. And the loss you can
actually just use the cross entropy loss
here. Um and so you can think about it
as you're doing a classification problem
for each dimension of your actions.
One other diagram that I think would be
helpful here to think about how we go
about doing this is
when you have a model that's kind of
auto reggressive that's predicting
actions, you often use a sequence model.
And so if you think about kind of a
sequence neural network something like a
transformer or something like that uh
you would pass as input your state and
then you passes as in then you're kind
of predicting a distribution over the
first dimension of your action. So this
is kind of a distribution over steering
angle. Then you would then kind of
sample from [clears throat] this
distribution
and then you'll pass this uh this
predict uh the sampled action or your
kind of chosen steering command back
into your model and then output the next
the distribution over the next action.
And this is exactly how language models
work where you'll um have some sort of
kind of beginning token. You'll predict
a distribution over the next word.
You'll sample a word from that. Um pass
that sampled word back into the model
and then predict a distribution over the
next word. Um except now we're doing it
over dimensions of our action sequence
rather than uh over different words in a
sentence. Yeah, great question. How do
you determine the order of these
different dimensions? Uh in language
models, it's very natural because like
there's a natural ordering to like words
in a sentence, for example, although
even across different languages, there's
some variation there. Um it's something
that generally you kind of pick by hand.
You could also in some ways treat it as
a hyperparameter. Um in other cases,
there might also be somewhat natural
choices for the ordering. So if you're
controlling a robot arm for example, um
you can kind of go down what's called
the kinematic chain of a robot arm where
you start with the kind of the base
dimension and then you go to the next
joint and the next joint um and so
forth. Uh the good news is that in
principle um the kind of the expressive
power of this distribution doesn't
change with the order. Um essentially
your goal is trying to represent the
full joint distribution over all
dimensions. And the only reason why
you're doing kind of an ordering here is
because um if you tried to represent
kind of a joint distribution over all
the dimensions at once, there's a lot of
um kind of pair-wise probabilities that
you would have to predict and it's a lot
more efficient to do it one more kind of
one dimension at a time to represent the
full joint. Yeah. So the question is um
in the case of like a video game it was
pretty discreet. Here we're in a more
continuous case. Um are we discretiz
like whenever we want to use an auto
reggressive model does that mean we
should be discretizing right cool. Um so
there's actually kind of two reasons to
be using um uh discretization. Uh one
reason to use discretization is it
allows you to model very multimodal
complex distributions. Uh and so you can
these the kind of these bars can be any
height that you want. And so it actually
can model things that are way more
expressive than a mixture of gausian up
to how fine your discretization is. Um
the challenge with discretization is
that if you have like a lot of bins like
you might have a 100 bins for one
dimension and then you're trying to um
represent like a I don't know 10
dimensional action or something like
that then the dimensionality of your
discretized actions is going to blow up
um if you try to model all like that
full 10 to the fifth um matrix over
probabilities. And so using an auto
reggressive model helps you deal with
that dimensionality.
Um you could in principle also use an
auto reggressive model with like a
mixture of gausian for example. Um and
that would be like completely fine as
well. Um this is yeah it's not like a a
common choice per se. Um because if
you're going to go through the trouble
of of using an autogressive model
usually discretization is like a pretty
powerful choice. Um but yeah, you can
also use it with like a gausian mixture
model or gausian or something like that.
Yeah. So the question was around how we
actually kind of train this and maybe
let's just like walk through how we go
about training this. So um it's actually
going to look uh well yeah let's let's
walk through how we train it. So we're
given some data set uh so we're given
uh some data set that has state action
pairs and we're going to want to train
our neural network and we're going to
follow a typical way of training neural
networks which is to sample uh to sample
an example from your data set uh or
sample a mini batch of examples. I'll
write it up for a mini batch size of one
um just for simplicity but you can uh
kind of extend it. So we're going to be
sampling a state action pair from our
data set and
the
once we sample this um
there
we will essentially be running a forward
pass through our network and a backward
pass through our network. And the key
question that comes up is like uh doing
the forward pass is kind of fairly
straightforward. Uh and when we do the
forward pass, we'll be getting kind of
some probability over the actions of
each dimension. And then we need to
figure out what should the objective be.
Uh and the objective that there's
actually kind of a common objective uh
that we can think about for all of these
generative models.
And that objective is that we want um
we're outputting these kind of
probability distributions. We want to be
maximizing the probability of the
actions represented in the data. uh or
equivalently
um we'll write this as minimizing the
log probability of I'll write this as pi
theta of a given s
um and this is with respect to theta
and so what this means is we're going to
be evaluating how likely is the action
that was sampled under our policy
um and then we'll be trying to make the
probability of the action in the data
set as high as possible or the negative
log probability as low as possible. Now
in practice what this what this log
probability looks like um is going to be
different for different models. uh for a
gausian mixture model what you'll do is
you can write down uh the probability
density function for a gausian gausian
mixture model um and then just
differentiate with respect to the mean
variance and weight that is outputed by
the neural network
and for the case of a
um kind of the auto reggressive model uh
it's a little bit different so we will
what this looks like for the auto
reggressive
is we will have um we essentially get
like the probability
of
um
a1
and the probability of a t2 given a t1
and so forth. And this probability uh
for this first dimension it will just be
the cross entropy loss um that
corresponds to trying to maximize the
log probability of this value for a
discrete categorical variable.
And for the second dimension, um, that's
where things get a little bit more
complicated because you'll have the this
this will just be the cross entropy
loss, but you need to figure out which
action you want to use here. And often
times you will use uh the action in the
data set. So um, for the inputs, you'll
often actually pass as input the state
and the dimensions that were chosen in
the data set. And then for each of these
probabilities, you'll be applying the
cross entropy loss uh and back
propagating the cross entropy loss back
into the network. And then at test time,
uh you'll then actually be using uh your
own predictions and passing your own
predictions into the neural network.
But this is really the um this objective
right here is really uh the core loss
function. And this corresponds to uh a
form of cross entropy loss uh for
discretized distributions um and for
gausian mixture models you write down
the PDF and differentiate. Yeah. Yeah.
So the question was it seems a little
odd to discretize and and do a
categorical distribution over a
continuous variable especially given
that a loss function like cross entropy
won't take into account the fact that
two bins are like that sort of error is
probably less costly than an error that
is uh that for two bins that are like
very far apart from one another. Um this
is kind of uh one downside to using
discretized uh kind of discrete
discretized actions. Um, in practice
often that sort of distance is something
that the uh is fairly quick to learn.
Um, and so the outcome is often uh still
pretty good. Uh, but you might need um
you might need more data and how fine
your discretization is a really
important hyperparameter because if it's
too fine uh then it'll be very hard to
get signal because um if you're off by
one uh you'll get like zero loss
function. There are also other things
that you can do to try to smoothen out
the the data um and smoothen out the
labels so that uh the label isn't just
um like a one hot vector. You can kind
of smooth around it a little bit. Um so
that's one thing that can also help with
that although uh it's a little bit more
advanced. Oh yeah, awesome question. I
didn't actually get to write the third
example. Um and so yeah, so when you are
outputting the probability over the
third action, it will be conditioned on
everything so far. And often the way
that you do that is if you're using a
sequence model, you can then output the
prediction like a sample from this
distribution. So a t
um and then output the probability over
the third action right here. And if you
have a sequence model that has that
takes into account everything from the
past then it will already condition on
all the actions so far. Um so how does
back propagation handle um this when
it's discreet? So uh only the output uh
is discrete. Uh and so you can think
about it as a classification problem. Uh
and so if the weights are discreet
that's that's bad for uh for back
propagation. But when it's only at the
labels you're only just computing the
loss function on those discrete
variables. And then that loss um is uh
you can yeah back propagate in a direct
way. Um and that's because you're yeah
comparing the the output is outputting a
probability um and uh computing a loss
on that probability and then you can
back propagate that loss on that
probability. So the outputs are actually
still uh continuous values because
you're outputting the the height of each
of these bars.
Cool. Um so this is a visualization of
this kind of discretized case. We're
outputting the um the first dimension,
the second dimension given the first
dimension, the third dimension given the
first two dimensions of the action and
so forth. Uh and this is very scalable.
It allows you to handle uh like fairly
long sequences of actions uh similar to
language models.
Uh the last thing that I put up on here
is diffusion. Uh diffusion is uh also a
very appealing choice especially for
continuous actions. It can model very
complex distributions over continuous
variables uh including highdimensional
continuous variables like images or
actions. And it does so by using this
kind of denoising process where you
start with complete noise and uh den
noiseise it uh iteratively to make it um
a less and less noisy version of the
action to ultimately generate um
hopefully a clean action prediction.
Uh and one thing that's kind of notable
is both dis both this model and
diffusion models do have some sort of
iterative process. Uh in the case of
auto reggressive models it's iterative
over the dimensions of your prediction
and in the case of diffusion it's
iterative over this denoising process.
Um now one question I have for all of
you. So we've talked about these more
expressive distribution classes.
Um, and none of what we talked about has
actually like really changed the
architecture of the model.
And I'm curious, um, one very important
question is instead of having these more
complex distributions, we could just
still use the L2 error like the L2 norm
as the loss function, but just make the
neural network bigger.
And bigger neural networks are generally
more expressive than smaller neural
networks. Um, so does anyone have
thoughts on how what we talked about
here is different from just making the
model bigger with the L2 law? Yeah. So
in the driving example, even if you make
the network like really really large,
it's still going to output just the
mean. It might output the mean very very
accurately. Uh, but it doesn't actually
change its ability to rep represent a
more complex distribution.
And so um the expressive power of a
distribution that you're trying to
represent is actually uh in many ways
like separate from the expressive power
of the function itself. Uh and if you
think about kind of this picture again
where you have a neural network that's
outputting parameters of a distribution.
There's the expressive part of this
function of how how like how many
functions can you represent that go from
s to parameters and then there's the
expressive power of this top part that
how many different distributions can
those parameters even represent in the
first place. Uh and this is a really
important point um where kind of neural
network expressivity is distinct often
distinct from distribution expressivity.
Yeah. So the expressivity of the of like
this output um
the expressivity of the distributions
that it can represent um is is kind of
captured by what you're what kind of
distribution you're allowing it to
represent. And if it only outputs mean
and variance, it can very expressively
represent functions that go from state
to mean and variance, but it can't
represent anything more complex than a
gausian.
Okay, so we we walked through this a
bit. So we are given some
demonstrations. We're trying to train a
generative model over actions. And this
is trying to minimize the um the log
likelihood of the negative log
likelihood of the experts actions given
um given the states in the
demonstration.
Um and so this equation looks I mean
maybe a little bit complicated. Uh but
the log pi is the log probability under
the policy. Um the the blue part is the
demo actions uh that are sampled from
the demonstration data set. Um and this
probability is under the policy that
we're trying to learn.
Um cool. And then once we fit this uh we
should have a policy that's better at
actually matching what the expert is
doing and as a result it should be
better at performing the test. Okay. Um
so now why did we learn all this? uh how
how well does the generative model work
compared to just using an L2 loss? Uh
there's a couple of works that have
evaluated this more explicitly. So
here's a a transport task where you need
to um have one robot uh kind of
transport a tool to another robot and
the policy is controlling both of these
robots.
Uh and we'll be comparing diffusion uh
and a gausian mixture model. diffusion
is actually is a lot more expressive
than what you can even represent with a
gausian mixture model. And we'll be
looking at two different demonstration
data sets. One was a data set that was
just collected by one person uh and then
the other one is a data set that was
collected by multiple people. And we'll
look at success rate.
Uh and we use diffusion. We see that um
on both data sets it's able to do pretty
well. uh although it does degrade with
multiple humans in the data set which
means that as you add more diversity in
the data set uh performance can go down.
Uh and with the gausian mixture model we
see that uh it well first it does worse
than diffusion. So expressivity is very
helpful expressive distributions is very
helpful and second it actually goes down
a lot more for the multihuman data set.
uh which means that uh like the
expressivity of the distribution is
especially important for data sets that
have more different kinds of um
behaviors in them.
Um we can also see this on a on a real
task on a real robot. So this is a task
that's actually pretty difficult uh
hanging a shirt on a hanger. Um it was
collected by uh the data set was
collected by lots of different people uh
because it's actually a pretty large
data set and once you scale up it's very
hard to have a single person with one
consistent strategy collect all of your
data. Uh so it was has different people
and different strategies and it compares
using either diffusion which is very
expressive or an L1 loss uh which is a
deterministic policy.
Uh and what we see first it's not as
successful as the the simpler simulated
task. Uh but here we see again that like
having a expressive distribution is
really critical for being able to do the
task successfully and if you just use L1
loss uh the success rate of the policy
uh drops by nearly 50%.
Is there any scenario where you'd want
to use a mixture of other models instead
of a gausian? Um oftentimes other models
are um might already like be quite
expressive. Uh so not not to my
knowledge uh but um it's not without uh
not like completely inconceivable. Yeah.
Okay. Um now if you actually look at
some of the like big models that people
have been developing uh in robotics. Uh
they build on what we covered uh so far
in lecture. Uh and so these are uh kind
of foundation models trained on lots of
different demonstration data sets uh by
companies like Nvidia, Figure, PI um and
uh this kind of open source vision
language action model using expressive
distributions when you have large scale
data sets is a key component of these
models
and uh if you look at some of the big
models that people have been developing
for autonomous driving at Whimo and Wave
uh the first one uses discretized uh and
auto reggressive prediction and the
second one also uses is discretized
actions with auto reggressive
prediction.
Great. So a summary so far of what we've
talked about. Um if you have data from
one consistent demonstrator, you should
learn a unimodal policy distribution.
If you have multimodal data from
multiple demonstrators, you should learn
a distribution. Uh you need an
expressive generative model. Uh when you
have data from multiple people, very
important.
Um and
one other thing that I'll mention here
is that the algorithm is fully offline.
Uh and this is getting into um a notion
that's very important in reinforcement
learning more generally. Uh which is
offline algorithms um are a bit
different from online algorithms. So
offline algorithms use only an existing
data set and they don't use any new data
from what you're learning.
And online means that you're using new
data from your learn policy. Uh and this
distinction is important in a couple
different ways. Um online means that the
you're going to have to actually kind of
recollect data as you run the algorithm.
Uh and so this is can be expensive. It
can also uh if your policy might be like
undertrained. In some scenarios, it
might be unsafe to run your policy. uh
like if you're in like a medical domain
for example, you might want to not want
to collect online data from a policy
that doesn't work fully yet. Um and so
there's there's kind of uh thinking
about offline algorithms and online
algorithms uh is generally uh yeah it's
a key distinction and a key way to think
about different algorithms.
Um so for what we've covered so far we
also uh we don't need any data from the
policy. So this is offline. Um we also
don't need to define a reward function.
Uh last time we talked about defining
reward functions for examples for some
examples and we talked about how uh in
some examples it might be kind of hard
to write down the reward function. So
this is pretty nice like in driving you
don't have to write down all of the ways
in which you might want it to drive.
Um the downside is that you might need a
lot of data for reliable performance.
You might need a lot of demonstrations.
Uh and that ties into how we might try
to learn from online interventions.
Yeah. So the question was um for the
kind of previous videos that I showed uh
imitation learning seems straightforward
like what is like the research in it um
uh and is it just doing what we talked
about today? Um there are a couple well
I guess there's a number of different
things that went into uh those different
examples. Uh the
so I can walk through I mean maybe a
couple examples. So in the case of the
first demonstration um the a lot of
things went into curation of the data um
and also the architecture of the model.
Uh and so those were two kind of things
that were novel about this. In the case
of the NVIDIA example, a lot of work
went into trying to use data from
simulation, especially because
collecting data on humanoids is quite
challenging and trying to figure out how
to leverage that simulation data. Um in
the case of the figure example, there
was also some uh architectural design
choices that made it helpful, especially
in terms of running models at very high
frequency. Um and in the open VA
example, that was also an example where
there's a lot of architectural choices
um in terms of the models. Uh and so
it's not just exactly what we talked
about. So there is a bit more to it. Um
but the what we talked about is a huge
driving factor behind these different
examples.
Um and these these two um a lot of that
also went into different like code
training objectives and and
architectures.
So uh we've talked about a lot about how
to um how to train models with imitation
learning and there's one important thing
that we haven't covered yet which is
what can go wrong and why imitation
learning is kind of challenging. So um
for this it's helpful to look at
supervised learning. So in supervised
learning we have some data uh and it's
usually kind of trained from one data
set that stays fixed uh and we try to
and kind of the um the inputs to the
model are completely independent from
the predictions that the model makes.
Now this all changes in imitation
learning. So uh say you have a
demonstration
that is in your data set and so each of
these dots is like a state uh and then
an action state action uh
something like this and now you're
trying to mimic this demonstration.
um if you're trying to mimic it and then
you roll out your policy the starting
from this state uh maybe at the
beginning of the trajectory uh it's able
to do pretty well. Uh but at some point
it might like make a mistake. The policy
isn't going to be perfect. And so if it
makes a mistake maybe it kind of ends up
over here a little further from where
the demonstration covered.
And now from this state, it's possible
that it actually doesn't have that much
data from where it ended up after it
made this mistake. Even if it was a
small mistake, it's going to be kind of
potentially under represented in the
data. And if it's underrepresented, it's
actually even more likely to make a
mistake in the future. And so if it's
more likely to make a mistake, it might
actually uh kind of drift away from the
distribution even more. And at that
point, maybe here it's actually very far
away and it makes maybe an even bigger
mistake.
So this is often referred to as
compounding errors because these
mistakes because they can start drifting
off the distribution when you make
mistakes, those mistakes can then
compound as you roll out your policy. Uh
and as a result of this um and kind of
one thing that you see here is that the
distribution of states this pen uh the
distribution of states that are visited
by your policy
is actually different from the
distribution of states that's visited by
the expert.
And
this means that uh you actually it kind
of it differs fundamentally from
supervised learning. Um so errors can
lead lay the way from the distribution.
Errors can then compound.
Um the states visited by the expert are
different than the states visited by the
learn policy. This is referred to as
covariant shift. So it's a kind of
distribution shift. Uh and that sort of
distribution shift can lead to um worse
performance
and also makes it different from
supervised learning.
So um this is one of the reasons why
fitting the distribution really well is
very important because you if you don't
fit it well and you learn only the mean
for example then you're even more likely
to have these kinds of compounding
errors.
Um but even and then even if you do fit
it well you might still make mistakes
and might drift off the distribution.
So how can we address this?
Um, one solution is just to collect a
ton of data, train for as long as
possible to fit the data as well as you
can and hope for the best. Um, if you
have the capacity to do this, it's not a
terrible solution. Uh, but there's also
some other solutions. Uh, and these
solutions are actually quite popular in
practice. And, uh, one of the basically
the the key alternative solution is to
try to collect corrective data. And so
if we're in this scenario, what we can
try to do is
um if as the policy starts to make a
mistake, we could try to say, okay, if
you're here um the correct action is to
do this. And this kind of green data can
be very very helpful to allow the policy
to recover from mistakes that it made.
Um, so the corrective behav data would
be kind of ideally you would learn kind
of something like this that tells your
policy exactly how to recover. And then
if you collect this corrective data,
then you could combine the data in green
with the data in black, train a policy
on that combined data.
And uh then if it makes a mistake, it
should actually have examples of how to
recover and get back to the distribution
because we're actually running our
policy and then getting examples of how
to recover after running our policy.
Does this not overfit the model and make
it less generalizable? Um you would need
to make sure that when you collect
online data, you collect it in diverse
scenarios and not just very narrow
scenarios. If you only collected in a
very small amount of scenarios then
these corrections won't be as diverse as
your original data set. Yeah. So the
main difference between the learn policy
distribution and the expert distribution
um it is just kind of uh how the actions
led to particular states. Um and the
reason yeah and this is I'm kind of
using this as shorthand for the states
visited uh by the policy. Um, and when
you start to incorporate these ex these
corrections, you're kind of expanding
the distributions of states that you
have data for, and you're kind of um
making your data set uh your
distribution of states seen in your data
set wider to include kind of both PBS
and um the states that your policy might
be likely to visit um if it makes
mistakes.
Um so in terms of what this looks like
as an algorithm, we will first roll out
our policy. So this is what's shown in
blue here. Then we will query an expert
at the states that you visited.
Um and these actions in green are the
same as kind of the orange a star on the
slide.
And then we will aggregate the
corrective data with the existing the
first demonstration data set.
And then we'll update the policy on the
aggregated data set.
Um and this updated policy you could
kind of fine-tune the policy. So kind of
warm start it um train on the original
data set uh and then update it with
fine-tuning. You could also train from
scratch if you're concerned about um I
don't know some biases or something like
that. that often times you might
fine-tune. Uh and then you can actually
repeat this process. So you can train on
the corrective data, get a better policy
and then maybe your policy actually
starts making you have kind of a another
policy and maybe it makes mistakes uh in
a different way and you in that case
you'd want to then kind of collect some
corrective data uh from that second
policy if a new failure mode or a new
kind of mistake emerges.
Um and so this sort of uh this is a sort
of repetitive process. Um this name has
a terrible algorithm uh because it's not
very descriptive but it's called data
set aggregation or dagger. Um because
you're aggregating data. Uh it's
important to helpful to know terminology
but this is uh I think was a bad choice.
Um and it's a data efficient way to
learn from an expert. Uh but it can be
hard to query an expert. Um and so
getting these green actions can be a
little bit tricky. So you might have to
actually ask a person like okay this is
what my my car did on the road like what
steering command should it have done
instead in those scenarios and so this
sort of data actually can be potentially
very hard to collect. Yeah. So how do we
get the corrective data? Um what this
would look like is you would uh run your
policy to get this blue trajectory. Um
and so this would be a uh this
trajectory is like a sequence of like
s1 a1 s2 a2 and so forth and then you
would basically like this is not
possible in some scenarios but you'd ask
a person like for this s what should the
a have been and for this s what should
the a have been and for this s what
should the a have been now there are
scenarios where you can't do that and
where this algorithm is just not
possible to
And that kind of leads into
um potentially a scenario like another
way that we might be able to collect
corrective data. We might not be able to
tell exactly like this is exactly the
steering command you should have done
because that's very hard to do. And so
what we could do instead is
instead of saying like for each of these
actions we want the we want to query
what the expert would have done. We're
actually going to let the expert take
full control at some point. And so what
this would look like is something where
you start drifting off. The expert
notices that a mistake was made and then
takes full control. Uh for example,
starts driving the car rather than
letting the policy drive the car. And
then in this case, you can then add that
those kind of partial demonstrations to
your data set instead of trying to query
the expert on the policy states. And so
here you would start to roll out the
learn policy. Um the expert intervenes
when the policy makes a mistake. Uh the
expert provides a partial demonstration
from the state that the policy visited.
Um so take full control and then
aggregate um this partial demonstrations
with the original data set um in order
to then update the policy and again you
can kind of repeat this process uh so
that you can cover different potential
failure modes of the policy. Yeah. Yeah.
So in all these cases the the best
performance of the policy is upper
bounded by the expert.
The question was if we're um detecting a
mistake is that mostly if you've played
with something or something else. Uh
this is something that's subjective and
uh is kind of up to the um up to the
demonstrator in many ways. Uh the
oftenimes you want to be a bit more pro
proactive and before the car hits
something you would want to take
control. And so one of the downsides of
this algorithm is that it can sometimes
be hard to catch mistakes quickly. Like
if the policy decides to like I don't
know drastically change the action and
it was unpredictable. Uh that can be
very hard to to proactively prevent. Um
and you want ideally this to be in a
scenario where you can predict um like
if the policy has started to drift into
another lane kind of recentering it that
sort of thing. Uh this is actually
something that uh companies do in
driving where they let the policy run.
they have a safety driver and then the
safety driver will take full control if
it seems like the policy either doesn't
know what to do and it's like stalling
um or uh it's starting to to make a
mistake that we've seen failure modes of
that. We've seen cases where safety
drivers were not able to prevent um a
mistake that was more major. Uh and so
there's downsides uh to this kind of
like kind of relying on the demonstrator
to uh to proactively prevent a huge
mistake from happening. Um but it is a
more kind of it is a practical interface
for providing corrections in a lot of
scenarios um and can help improve
performance significantly.
Yeah. So the question was if you're can
you explain again why if you're
correcting a narrow corrective data why
that would lead to overfitting. Um so
let's take the driving example. If your
original driving data was like all over
the United States and then your
corrective driving data was only on
Stanford's campus, then uh when you
combine the data set, uh it might uh
only learn kind of that corrective
behavior in a more narrow set of
scenarios and might also overfit to the
Stanford data um leading to a policy
that is perhaps less generalizable. And
ideally, when you corrected corre
collected corrective data, it would be
in a broader set of scenarios than
campus.